<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Tear Down This Wall Speech: Digital Transcription </title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoded by</resp>
                    <name>Pietro Tisci</name>
                    <name>Sergei Slinkin</name>
                    <name>Yifan Wu</name>
                </respStmt>             
            </titleStmt>
        
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Ronald Reagan Library</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Simi Valley, CA 93065</pubPlace>
                <availability>
                    <p>Open access</p>
                </availability>
                <date when="1987">1987</date>
            </publicationStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <title level="a">Remarks at Brandenberg Gate, Berlin, Germany [President's Speaking Copy]</title>
                    <author>Ronald Reagan</author>
                    <publisher>Ronald Reagan Library</publisher>
                    <date>1987</date>. 
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>

        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="speech">
                <head>Tear Down This Wall!</head>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Ronald Reagan</speaker>
                    <p>
                        <persName ref="#Kohl" role="Chancellor">Chancellor Kohl</persName>,
                        <persName ref="#Diepgen" role="Governing Mayor">Governing Mayor Diepgen</persName>,
                        ladies and gentlemen: <date when="1963-06-26">Twenty-four years ago</date>,
                        <persName ref="#Kennedy" role="President">President John F. Kennedy</persName>
                        visited <placeName ref="#Berlin">Berlin</placeName>, speaking to the people of this city and the world at the <placeName ref="#CityHall">City Hall</placeName>. Well, since then
                        <rs type="person">two other presidents</rs> have come, each in his turn, to <placeName ref="#Berlin">Berlin</placeName>. And <date when="1987-06-12">today</date> 
                        <persName ref="#Reagan">I</persName>, myself, make my second visit to your <placeName ref="#Berlin">city</placeName>.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        We come to <placeName ref="#Berlin">Berlin</placeName>, we American <rs type="person">presidents</rs>, because it’s our duty to speak, in
                        this place, of freedom. But I must confess, we’re drawn here by other things as
                        well: by the feeling of history in this <placeName ref="#Berlin">city</placeName>, more than 500 years older than our own
                        <placeName ref="#America">nation</placeName>; by the beauty of the <placeName ref="#Grunewald">Grunewald</placeName> and the <placeName ref="#Tiergarten">Tiergarten</placeName>; most of all, by your
                        courage and determination. Perhaps the composer <persName ref="#Lincke">Paul Lincke</persName> understood
                        something about American <rs type="person">presidents</rs>. You see, like so many <rs type="person">presidents</rs> before
                        me, I come here <date when="1987-06-12">today</date> because wherever I go, whatever I do: <q><foreign xml:lang="de">Ich hab noch einen
                        Koffer in <placeName ref="#Berlin">Berlin</placeName>.</foreign> [I still have a suitcase in Berlin.]</q>
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Our gathering <date when="1987-06-12">today</date> is being broadcast throughout <placeName ref="#WesternEurope">Western Europe</placeName> and <placeName ref="#NorthAmerica">North
                        America</placeName>. I understand that it is being seen and heard as well in the <placeName ref="#East">East</placeName>. To those
                        listening throughout <placeName ref="#EasternEurope">Eastern Europe</placeName>, a special word: Although I cannot be with
                        you, I address my remarks to you just as surely as to those standing here before
                        me. For I join you, as I join your fellow countrymen in the West, in this firm, this
                        unalterable belief: <q><foreign xml:lang="de">Es gibt nur ein <placeName ref="#Berlin">Berlin</placeName>.</foreign> [There is only one Berlin.]</q>
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Behind me stands a <object>wall</object> that encircles the free sectors of this <placeName ref="#Berlin">city</placeName>, part of a vast
                        system of <object>barriers</object> that divides the entire continent of <placeName ref="#Europe">Europe</placeName>. From the <placeName ref="#Baltic">Baltic</placeName>,
                        south, those <object>barriers</object> cut across <placeName ref="#Germany">Germany</placeName> in a gash of <object>barbed wire</object>, <object>concrete</object>, <object>dog
                        runs</object>, and <object>guard towers</object>. Farther south, there may be no visible, no obvious <object>wall</object>.
                        But there remain armed guards and checkpoints all the same—still a restriction
                        on the right to travel, still an instrument to impose upon ordinary men and women
                        the will of a totalitarian state. Yet it is here in <placeName ref="#Berlin">Berlin</placeName> where the <object>wall</object> emerges most
                        clearly; here, cutting across your city, where the <object>news photo</object> and the <object>television
                        screen</object> have imprinted this brutal division of a continent upon the mind of the
                        world. Standing before the <placeName ref="#BrandenburgGate">Brandenburg Gate</placeName>, every man is a German, separated
                        from his fellow men. Every man is a Berliner, forced to look upon a scar.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        <persName ref="#Weizsacker" role="President">President von Weizsacker</persName> has said, <q>“The German question is open as long as the
                        <placeName ref="#BrandenburgGate">Brandenburg Gate</placeName> is closed.” </q><date when="1987-06-12">Today</date> I say: As long as the gate is closed, as long
                        as this scar of a <object>wall</object> is permitted to stand, it is not the German question alone
                        that remains open, but the question of freedom for all mankind. Yet I do not come
                        here to lament. For I find in <placeName ref="#Berlin">Berlin</placeName> a message of hope, even in the shadow of this
                        <object>wall</object>, a message of triumph.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        In this season of <date notBefore="1945-03-01" notAfter="1945-05-31">spring in 1945</date>, the people of <placeName ref="#Berlin">Berlin</placeName> emerged from their air-raid
                        shelters to find devastation. Thousands of miles away, the people of <placeName ref="#TheUnitedStates">the United
                        States</placeName> reached out to help. And in <date when="1947-06-05">1947</date> Secretary of State—as you’ve been told—
                        <persName ref="#Marshall">George Marshall</persName> announced the creation of what would become known as the
                        <activity><term>Marshall Plan</term></activity>. Speaking precisely <date when="1947-06-05">40 years ago this month</date>, he said: <q>“Our policy is
                        directed not against any country or doctrine, but against hunger, poverty,
                        desperation, and chaos.”</q>
                    </p>
                    <p>In the <placeName ref="#Reichstag">Reichstag</placeName> <date when="1987-06-12">a few moments ago</date>, I saw a <event>display</event> commemorating this 40th
                        anniversary of the <activity><term>Marshall Plan</term></activity>. I was struck by the sign on a burnt-out, gutted
                        structure that was being rebuilt. I understand that Berliners of my own generation
                        can remember seeing signs like it dotted throughout the western sectors of the
                        <placeName ref="#Berlin">city</placeName>. The sign read simply: “The <activity><term>Marshall Plan</term></activity> is helping here to strengthen the
                        free world.” A strong, free world in <placeName ref="#West">the West</placeName>, that dream became real. <placeName ref="#Japan">Japan</placeName> rose
                        from ruin to become an <term>economic giant</term>. <placeName ref="#Italy">Italy</placeName>, <placeName ref="#France">France</placeName>, <placeName ref="#Belgium">Belgium</placeName>—virtually every
                        nation in <placeName ref="#WesternEurope">Western Europe</placeName> saw <term>political and economic rebirth</term>; the <orgName ref="#EuropeanCommunity">European
                        Community</orgName> was founded.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        In <placeName ref="#WestGermany">West Germany</placeName> and here in <placeName ref="#Berlin">Berlin</placeName>, there took place an <term>economic
                        miracle</term>, the <foreign xml:lang="de"><term>Wirtschaftswunder</term></foreign>, so prosperous, so thriving that this <placeName ref="#Berlin">city</placeName> in fact
                        became one of the wonders of the world. Perhaps this gets to the root of the
                        matter, to the most fundamental distinction of all. The totalitarian world produces
                        backwardness because it does such violence to the spirit, thwarting the human
                        impulse to create, to enjoy, to worship. The totalitarian world finds even symbols
                        of love and of worship an affront. Years ago, before the <rs type="person" ref="#EastGermans">East Germans</rs> began
                        rebuilding their churches, they erected a secular structure: the <object>TV tower</object> at
                        <placeName ref="#AlexPlatz">Alexanderplatz</placeName>. Virtually ever since, the authorities have been working to correct
                        the tower’s one unintended defect: with the sun shining on it, the <object>sphere</object> that
                        crowns the tower creates the sign of the cross. There in <placeName ref="#Berlin">Berlin</placeName>, like the <placeName ref="#Berlin">city</placeName> itself,
                        symbols of love, symbols of worship, cannot be suppressed.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        As I looked out a moment ago from the <placeName ref="#Reichstag">Reichstag</placeName>, that embodiment of <term>German unity</term>, I
                        noticed words crudely spray-painted upon the <object>walls</object>, perhaps by a <rs type="person" ref="#youngBerliner">young Berliner</rs>:
                        <q>“This <object>wall</object> will fall. Beliefs become reality.”</q> Yes, across <placeName ref="#Europe">Europe</placeName>, this <object>wall</object> will fall.
                        For it cannot withstand faith; it cannot withstand truth. The <object>wall</object> cannot
                        withstand freedom. And I would like, before I close, to say one word to the people
                        of the <placeName ref="#East">East</placeName>. I invite <persName ref="#Gorbachev">Mr. Gorbachev</persName>, <persName ref="#Gorbachev">Mr. Gorbachev</persName>, to speak his own words as
                        well. Let us not speak of the <object>walls</object> and the <object>barriers</object> that divide us, but of the
                        <object>bridges</object> that unite us. Let us not speak of the fears and the horrors, but of the hopes
                        and the dreams.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Because of this <object>wall</object>, because of the consequences of its existence, because of the
                        obstacles it represents, there is one sign the <rs type="person" ref="#Soviets">Soviets</rs> can make that would be
                        unmistakable, that would advance dramatically the cause of freedom and peace.
                        <persName ref="#Gorbachev" role="#GeneralSecretary">General Secretary Gorbachev</persName>, if you seek peace, if you seek prosperity for the <placeName ref="#SovietUnion">Soviet
                        Union</placeName> and <placeName ref="#EasternEurope">Eastern Europe</placeName>, if you seek <term>liberalization</term>: Come here to this gate!
                        <persName ref="#Gorbachev">Mr. Gorbachev</persName>, open this gate! <persName ref="#Gorbachev">Mr. Gorbachev</persName>, tear down this <object>wall</object>!
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        I understand the fear of war and the pain of division that afflict this continent—
                        and I pledge to you my country’s efforts to help overcome these burdens. But I
                        believe we must act now to remove the <term>obstacles</term> to peace and prosperity. I urge
                        the <placeName ref="#SovietUnion">Soviet Union</placeName> to work toward a new partnership, a partnership that builds upon
                        the realities of today’s <placeName ref="#Europe">Europe</placeName>. You, you who have been in the East, you who have
                        been in the West, let us take a moment now to reflect on the world we live in.
                        Imagine if we could tear down these <object>walls</object>, and build bridges to bring together our
                        people. There is no question, there is no question that in the minds of the men
                        and women of the East, the <object>wall</object> will fall. It will fall because it is the
                        will of history; it will fall because it is the will of humanity.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Today, as I stand before this historic gate, I ask you to tear down the <object>wall</object>.
                        Let us stand united as one people, let us work together to achieve our goals of
                        peace, freedom, and prosperity for all. Let us tear down the <object>barriers</object> that separate us.
                        Let us work for the day when all Germans, all Europeans, and indeed all people
                        of the world can live in freedom and in peace.
                    </p>
                </sp>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>